Guide to the Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation, Director’s Office records 1939-2007
Montana Historical Society
Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation, Director’s Office records
1939-2007
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 443
Montana. Department of Natural Resources and Conservation.
12 linear feet of shelf space
This collection is comprised of records of the Department of Natural Resources and Conservation, Director’s Office records including correspondence, subject files, and records collected by the director on the Montana Governor’s Council on Natural Resources and Development (GCNRD) and Water Resources Board.
"Helping to ensure that Montana's land and water resources provide benefits for present and future generations" is the mission of the Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation (DNRC). First established in 1971 as a result of the Executive Reorganization Act of 1971, the DNRC provides leadership in managing the state's natural resources. It is presently responsible for promoting the stewardship of Montana's water, soil, forest, and rangeland resources; for regulating forest practices and oil and gas exploration and production.
Nine boards and commissions are attached to the department. Six of them—the Board of Land Commissioners, Reserved Water Rights Compact Commission, Board of Oil and Gas Conservation, Board of Water Well Contractors, Flathead Basin Commission, and Montana Grass Conservation Commission—have decision-making authority. The other three—the Resource Conservation Advisory Council, Rangeland Resources Committee, and Drought Advisory Committee—act in an advisory capacity only.
The department is organized into seven divisions: Director's Office, Conservation and Resource Development Division (CARDD), Forestry, Oil and Gas Conservation, Reserved Water Rights Compact Commission, Trust Land Management, and Water Resources. Two of the divisions—the Oil and Gas Conservation Division and the Reserved Water Rights Compact Commission—are attached to the department for administrative purposes only.
The Director’s Office carries out the department’s mission and statutory responsibilities by administering, managing, planning, and evaluating total agency performance. The director oversees the development of appropriate policies and procedures throughout all organizational units of the agency and makes sure the structure supports optimum efficiency, consistency and capability for planning, consultation and decision-making.
The Director’s Office includes the director’s staff, a Public Affairs Office, a centralized Legal Unit, and a centralized Human Resources Office. The Financial Services Office is an extension of the director’s responsibility, and ability to provide budgeting, accounting, procurement, and contract management. The Office of Information Technology provides agency-wide services and support for network administration, applications and website development, and customer services.
This collection is composed of one series and two sub-series.
Series I is comprised of correspondence and subject files. Correspondence is arranged by year, and then alphabetically by subject. Subject files are arranged alphabetically.
Sub-series I and II represent records of the Montana Governor’s Council on Natural Resources and Development (GCNRD) and Water Resources Board (previously the State Water Conservation Board), respectively, that were collected by DNRC’s Director in the course of his duties.
This collection is arranged by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Environmental protection—Montana; Water-supply; Mining – Montana
Montana; Environmental Activism; Water and Water Rights
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Department of Natural Resources and Conservation, Director’s Office
  - Correspondence
    - General Correspondence, 1972 January– 1976 December (Box-folder 1 / 1-3 / 4)
    - Advisory Councils, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - Alternative Energy Advisory Council, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Bechtel Incorporated, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - Bonneville Regional Advisory Council, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
    - Bonneville Power Administration, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
    - Budget and Program Planning, 1976 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - Bureau of Land Management, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
    - Bureau of Reclamation, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
    - Burlington-Northern, Inc. [easement Request], 1972-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
    - Conservation Districts, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
    - Conservation Districts Division, 1977 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
    - Constituents [letters from], 2007 January – December (Box-folder 3 / 16-17)
    - Department of State Lands, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
    - Energy Planning Division, 1976 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - Environmental Defense Fund, 1973 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1973 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Department of Administration, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
    - Department of the Interior, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
    - Economic Development Association of Eastern Montana, 1972 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
    - Energy, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
    - Federal Energy Impact Assistance, 1976 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
    - Federal Resource Agency Reorganization, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
    - Federal of Rocky Mountain States, Inc., 1977 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
    - Forestry Division, 1976 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
    - “General Correspondence on Colstrip Study”, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
    - Legal Unit, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
    - Letters [Director], 1972 (Box-folder 4 / 15)
    - [DNRC] Library, 1978 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
    - Montana State University, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 4 / 17)
    - “Nuclear Siting” [Nuclear Regulatory Reform Act], 1977 (Box-folder 4 / 18)
    - Office of the Governor, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 4 / 19-5 / 4)
    - “Organization – DNRC”, 1977 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
    - “P.L. 566 Watershed Project Planning”, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
    - Renewable, Alternative Energy Sources, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
    - Resource Development Program, Water Development Bureau, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 5 / 8)
    - Resource Planning Act, 1977 (Box-folder 5 / 9)
    - Rural Environmental Assistance Program, 1973 (Box-folder 5 / 10)
    - Shoup, Richard G. [Congressman], 1973-1974 (Box-folder 5 / 11)
    - Special Staff Unit, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 12)
    - “United States Canadian Border Fence”, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5 / 13)
    - Water Resources Division, 1975 (Box-folder 5 / 14-15)
  - Subject Files
    - Atomic Energy [in obtaining water], 1967 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
    - [Balanced Growth Task Force Issue papers], ca. 1979 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
    - Bureau of Reclamation, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
    - [Cases, C.J. Dousman], 1942-1945 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Civil Defense [re: Montana streams travel Times], 1965 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - College Water Research, 1965 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
    - Colorado River [Colorado River Board, Colorado River Association of California], 1966-1967 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - Columbia Plateau Resources Council, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - Department of Agriculture, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
    - Department of Health [Montana], 1972-1973 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
    - Department of Intergovernmental Affairs Notice of Surplus Determination – Government Property in Columbia Falls, Whitefish], 1973 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
    - Department of the Interior, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 6 / 12)
    - D’Ewart, Wesley A., 1967-1968 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
    - Davis, Clarence A., 1962-1968 (Box-folder 6 / 14)
    - Energy, Environment and Natural Resources Balanced Growth Task Force, 1978 (Box-folder 6 / 15)
    - Energy Conservation, 1976 (Box-folder 6 / 16)
    - EPA Grant Status [Montana Environmental Quality Council], 1971 (Box-folder 6 / 17)
    - Environmental Quality Council, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 6 / 18)
    - Forest Practices Advisory Council, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 6 / 19)
    - Gianelli, William, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 6 / 20)
    - “Governor’s Forums” [Governor’s Public Forums on the Economy], 1977 (Box-folder 6 / 21-22)
    - Grass Conservation Commission, 1960-1971 (Box-folder 6 / 23)
    - Hiplex Program, 1976 (Box-folder 6 / 24)
    - Howard v. Howard [C.J. Dousman], 1942-1946 (Box-folder 6 / 25-7 / 1)
    - Inland Empire Waterways Association, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 7 / 2-3)
    - Interstate Conference on Water Problems, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 7 / 4-5)
    - Land and Water Conservation Fund, 1968 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
    - [State Legislation/Legislature], 1950-1969 (Box-folder 7 / 7-11)
    - Libby Re-regulation Dam Project, 1978 (Box-folder 7 / 12)
    - “Miscellaneous Meetings”, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 7 / 13)
    - Mississippi River, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 7 / 14)
    - Missouri River Basin Inter-Agency Committee, 1962-1968 (Box-folder 7 / 15-16)
    - Missouri River States Committee, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 7 / 17)
    - Missouri Valley Association, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 7 / 18-19)
    - Montana Association of Conservation Districts, 1975 (Box-folder 7 / 20)
    - Montana Energy Advisory Council, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 21)
    - Montana Energy Conservation plan, 1977 (Box-folder 7 / 22)
    - Montana Reclamation Association, 1965 (Box-folder 7 / 23)
    - Montana State Rural Areas Development, 1971 (Box-folder 7 / 24)
    - Montana University Joint Water Resources Research Center, 1968 (Box-folder 7 / 25)
    - Montana Water Congress, 1968 (Box-folder 7 / 26)
    - Montana Water Development Association, 1967 (Box-folder 7 / 27)
    - Montana Water Development Council, 1969 (Box-folder 7 / 28)
    - National Governors’ Conference [Sub- Committee reports], 1967 (Box-folder 7 / 29)
    - National Reclamation Association, 1968 (Box-folder 7 / 30)
    - Non-degradation Policy, 1968 (Box-folder 8 / 1)
    - National Water Commission, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 8 / 2-4)
    - News Releases and Speeches, 1974-1978 (Box-folder 8 / 5-6)
    - Northwest Electricity Task Force, 1977 (Box-folder 8 / 7)
    - Pacific Marine Fisheries Commission [Resolution No. 11], 1969 (Box-folder 8 / 8)
    - Pacific Northwest Water Development, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 8 / 9)
    - Pollution, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 8 / 10-11)
    - Proposed Legislation [includes Colorado River Basin project], 1963-1969 (Box-folder 8 / 12)
    - “Public Involvement”, 1979 (Box-folder 8 / 13)
    - Reclamation – Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
    - Senate Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 8 / 15)
    - Soil Conservation Service, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 8 / 16)
    - Special Staff, Staff Meetings, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 8 / 17-18)
    - State Conservation Commission Meetings, 1972 (Box-folder 8 / 19)
    - State Water Conservation Board, Legal Issues, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 8 / 20)
    - State Water Conservation Board, Legal Opinions, undated (Box-folder 8 / 21)
    - State Water Conservation Board, Misc., 1949-1963 (Box-folder 9 / 1)
    - [Statement by Director Gary Wicks, re: coal], undated (Box-folder 9 / 2)
    - Upper Missouri Water Users Association, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 9 / 3)
    - “Ward, Sylvester Murder – Missoula”, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 9 / 4)
    - Water for the West – Regional Plans”, 1969 (Box-folder 9 / 5)
    - Water Research Center, 1970 (Box-folder 9 / 6)
    - Water Resources Board, 1961-1970 (Box-folder 9 / 7-9)
    - Water Resources Council, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 9 / 10-11)
    - Water Right Act of 1968 (Box-folder 9 / 12)
    - Water Quality Management Plan, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 9 / 13)
    - Water and Water Courses, circa 1940 (Box-folder 9 / 14)
    - Western Governors’ Conference, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 9 / 15)
    - Western Governors’ Task Force, 1977 (Box-folder 9 / 16)
    - Western Interstate Water Conference, 1959-1970 (Box-folder 9 / 17)
    - Western Regional Drought Action Task Force (WDRATF), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 9 / 18-19)
    - Western States Water Augmentation Concept, 1968 (Box-folder 9 / 20)
- Montana Governor’s Council on Natural Resources and Development
  - Minutes
    - Governor’s Council on Natural Resources And Development (GCNRD), 1962-1971 (Box-folder 10 / 1-6)
    - Interdepartmental Advisory Council on Natural Resources (IACNR), 1953-1961 (Box-folder 10 / 7-8)
  - Subject Files
    - IACNR, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 10 / 9-11)
    - GCNRD, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10 / 12)
    - GCNRD, Annual Report, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 10 / 13)
    - GCNRD, Blackfoot River proposals, 1970 (Box-folder 10 / 14)
    - GCNRD, Buffalo Creek Area Study [reports and miscellaneous], 1968 (Box-folder 10 / 15-16)
    - GCNRD, Coal and Water report, 1971 (Box-folder 10 / 17)
    - GCNRD, “Compound 1080”, 1970 (Box-folder 10 / 18)
    - GCNRD, Environmental Coordinating Committee, 1971 (Box-folder 10 / 19)
    - GCNRD, Environmental Policy, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10 / 20)
    - GCNRD, Financial Reports, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 10 / 21)
    - GCNRD, Geologic Atlas, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 10 / 22)
    - GCNRD, Landscape Architect, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10 / 23)
    - GCNRD, Legislative Auditor’s Committee, 1971 (Box-folder 10 / 24)
    - GCNRD, Mined Land Reclamation, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 1)
    - GCNRD, Miscellaneous, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 11 / 2)
    - GCNRD, Modern Water Code, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 3)
    - GCNRD, Mosquito Abatement Advisory Council, 1971 (Box-folder 11 / 4)
    - GCNRD, Montana Wildlife Federation, 1971 (Box-folder 11 / 5)
    - GCNRD, Newlan Creek Watershed Work Plan, 1969 (Box-folder 11 / 6)
    - GCNRD, Nuclear Compact, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 7)
    - GCNRD, Pesticides, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 11 / 8)
    - GCNRD, Pollution Control Activities, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 9)
    - GCNRD, Prairie Dog Town [Greycliff], 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 10)
    - GCNRD, Public Domain Lands Proposed Classification, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 11)
    - GCNRD, Rangeland Resource Plan, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 12)
    - GCNRD, “A Review of Montana Law as it Pertains to the Problem of Making Recreation A Beneficial Use of Water”, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 13)
    - GCNRD, Refuse Act of 1899, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 11 / 14)
    - GCNRD, Road Improvement in the Fort Peck Area, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 15)
    - GCNRD, Smith River Planning, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 16)
    - GCNRD, Science and Technology, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 17)
    - GCNRD, Sun River Project at Great Falls, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 18)
    - GCNRD, Water Activities Summaries, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 11 / 19)
    - GCNRD, Water Policy, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 20)
    - GCNRD, Wilderness Act, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 21)
    - GCNRD, Wild and Scenic Rivers, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 11 / 22)
- Water Resources Board
  - Minutes
    - Water Resources Board [formerly the State Water Conservation Board], Meetings, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 11 / 23-24)
  - Subject Files
    - WRB, Accounting Report, 1969 June, 1970 (Box-folder 11 / 25)
    - WRB, Director [Douglas Smith], 1969-1971 (Box-folder 11 / 26-27)
    - WRB, Executive Reorganization, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 11 / 28)
    - WRB, Meetings [packets of information gathered for meetings], 1969 December – 1971 November (Box-folder 12 / 1-10)